Rhiannon: When a child’s behaviour seems
different from his or her peers, there
may be concerns that, “something is wrong
with them.” Although children develop at
different rates, a clinical assessment
from a professional and possibly some
early intervention, can be helpful.
As they get older, the question of a
mental health diagnosis may come up
because a child or adolescent who has
been progressing fine, suddenly becomes
very angry, sad, or worried all the time.
Leah: There are no definitive
medical tests to detect whether
someone has a mental health disorder
such as a blood test or scan.
Mental health diagnoses are based on
clinical interviews, observations,
and sometimes tasks and tests
the child is asked to complete.
The positives of having a mental
health diagnosis are that it gives
access to specialised services and
can help by giving the problem a name.
By giving it a name, it means someone
has seen it before, they are not alone,
and information can be shared with
others experiencing similar problems.
Rhiannon: By having a name, it also makes
it easier to explain the issues to others
and maybe access specific help as the
illness becomes the problem not the child.
Mental health diagnoses can be
presented as a fixed part of a
person, but it is also important
to consider that things change over
time and a mental health diagnosis
is not always a diagnosis for life.
Leah: There are also alternatives
to having a mental health diagnosis.
Mental health professionals may
work to understand the problem in
the child or young person’s family,
social and educational context,
without necessarily feeling the
need to give a formal diagnosis.
Rhiannon: They may also look at
what is the overall problem that is
creating the mental health issues,
and how does the child’s interactions
with others effect the problem?
Clinical interventions and strategies
can be used with both parents and
children without the need for a formal
diagnosis, and a diagnosis is not always
necessary to access therapy or support.